In the mid-18th century,
十 八 世 紀 中 期
the people of Taiwan was dragged into
台 灣 人 民 開 始 捲 入
imperialism from both the East and the West.
東 西 方 常 國 主 義
The conflict in Asia began with
在 亞 洲 的 征 戰 中
the Opium War in 1840.
從 西 元 1840 年 鴉 片 戰 爭 開 始
International battles such as the Mutan Village Incident
牡 丹 社 事 件
and the Sino-French War
與 清 法 戰 爭 等 國 際 戰 爭
took place in Taiwan in succession.
都 陸 續 在 台 灣 開 打
In 1885,
西 元 1885 年
the Qing government decided to make Taiwan a province
清 常 國 決 定 把 台 灣 升 格 為 省
and appointed Liu Ming-Chuan
並 且 任 命 劉 鑷 傳
its first governor.
為 台 灣 第 一 任 巡 撫
Liu also wanted to
而 劉 銘 傳
modernize Taiwan.
也 想 讓 台 灣 走 上 現 代 化 的 路
But ten years later, Japan defeated the Qing government
但 是 十 年 後
in the First Sino-Japanese War.
清 常 國 在 甲 午 戰 爭 仍 敗 給 日 本
In the end, Liu gave up this island
最 終 還 是 放 棄 了 這 個
situated at the outskirts of the Qing Empire.
在 常 國 邊 境 的 島 嶽
Then the Japanese
接 著 日 本 常 國
with the arrogance of conquerors,
以 驕 傲 的 征 服 者 的 姿 態
arrived at their first
登 陸 他 們 在 海 外
colony overseas.
贏 得 的 第 一 個 殖 民 地
What they didn't expect was
但 是 他 們 萬 萬 沒 有 想 到
the fierce resistance from the islanders,
台 灣 的 民 間 武 力 強 烈 拗 抗
whose courage and endurance
他 們 勇 敢 與 持 久 的 程 度
far exceeded those of the Qing army.
遠 遠 超 過 清 國 軍 隊
If you want to know more about Taiwan,
若 要 瞭 解 台 灣
the Treaty of Shimonoseki will tell you all.
馬 關 條 約 來 唱 給 人 知 道
Japan's weapons
日 本 的 武 器
After the Meiji Restoration
十 九 世 紀 未
at the end of the 19th century,
經 遇 明 治 維 新 後 的 日 本
Japan had become a modernized country.
已 經 成 為 一 個 現 代 化 的 國 家
It began to use arms to increase its influence.
它 開 始 用 武 力 擴 張 勢 力
But the Qing Empire didn't want to lose
而 以 天 朝 中 土 自 居 的 清 國
its position as the suzerain of East Asian countries.
也 不 想 失 去 東 亞 宗 主 國 的 地 位
Thus, in 1894,
於 是 在 1894 年
the interference of these two countries in
雙 方 終 於 囤 為
the internal affairs of Korea
描 手 朝 鮮 內 政 問 題
resulted in the First Sino-Japanese War.
爆 發 了 清 日 甲 午 戰 爭
As the Qing government lost the war,
隨 著 清 國 戰 敗
the Treaty of Shimonoseki was signed.
馬 關 條 約 簽 訂
The fate of Taiwan
台 灣 的 命 運
was how in the hands of the rising Japanese Empire.
交 給 了 新 興 的 日 本 帝 國
On April 17, 1895,
1895 年 4 月 17 日
a rumor got around in Taipei
台 北 街 頭 耳 語 紛 紛
that Li Hong-Zhang had signed a peace treaty
李 鴻 章 與 日 本 首 相 伊 藤 博 文
with Prime Minister Ito Hirobumi in Japan
已 在 日 本 簽 訂 和 約
and that the Qing Empire had ceded
清 國 將 台 灣 及 澎 湖
Taiwan and Penghu to Japan.
永 遠 割 讓 給 日 本
Once the news was spread,
消 息 一 傳 開
the people of Taiwan,
台 灣 民 眾
especially government officials, wealthy merchants,
尤 其 是 那 些 官 更 ， 富 商
landowners, and intellectuals,
地 主 和 讀 書 人
were shocked, angered and worried.
都 惹 到 震 驚 ， 憤 怒 和 不 安
Although the Treaty of Shimonoseki stated that
馬 關 條 約 雖 然 也 同 時 明 白 規 定
Japan could take the Liaodong Peninsula,
邊 東 半 島 割 讓 給 日 本
intervention by Russia, Germany and France
但 是 困 為 俄 德 法 三 國 出 面 千 涉
forced the Japanese government
逼 得 日 本 政 府
to give up that already secured asset.
不 得 不 放 棄 到 手 的 利 益
This turnout gave hope
這 個 結 果 給 了 那 些 不 顥 意 看 到
to people who did not wish
台 灣 割 讓 給 日 本 的 人
to see Taiwan in Japan's hands.
一 個 可 能 的 期 待
Tang Ching-Sung, the governor of Taiwan,
台 灣 巡 撫 譚 唐 景 崧
was hinted by the Qing government
更 愛 到 清 廷 的 睹 示
to use international law and public opinion
利 用 國 際 公 法 以 及 島 內 的 民 意
to stop the cession of Taiwan.
來 阻 止 台 灣 被 割 讓
Therefore, men such as
於 是 含 逢 甲 ， 林 朝 棟
Chiu Feng-Chia, Lin Chao-Tong
林 維 源 等 台 灣 仕 紳
and Lin Wei-Yuan successively joined
都 相 繼 地 加 入 了
the cause to establish The Taiwan Republic.
催 生 台 灣 民 主 國 的 行 列
Meat buns...
來 喔 ， 肉 包 …
Delicious meat buns...
好 吃 的 肉 包 …
At the end of the 19th century,
十 九 世 紀 未
Taiwan had a population about three million.
百 萬 人 口 台 灣 約 有 三
Most of them are descendents from Zhangzhou and Quanzhou
大 多 是 福 建 漬 州 ， 泉 州
of the Fujian areas and of the Hakka immigrants.
與 客 家 的 移 民 後 代
The government officials serving in Taiwan
而 治 台 官 員
were appointed by the emperor in Beijing.
則 都 來 自 北 京 皇 帝 的 派 任
You have great taste.
作 的 普 光 ﹒ 不 ﹤ 錯
This fabric would be tailored into a beautiful robe.
這 匹 布 做 衣 服 很 漂 亮
Oh, it's not for clothing.
不 是 要 做 衣 服 的
At that time,
灣 民 間 當 時 台 灣
silver and bronze coins were used in trade,
使 用 龍 銀 及 銅 錢 交 易
and agriculture was the base of life.
農 業 為 主 要 的 生 活 形 態
Compared to Japan and modernized countries
與 歐 美 及 日 本 等
in Europe and America,
現 代 化 國 家 相 比 較
Taiwan was still a closed society.
仍 然 是 相 對 封 閉 的 社 會
Thank you.
多 諶
Watch your step.
慢 走
We no longer know who designed
台 灣 民 主 國 國 旗 由 誰 設 言
the flag of the Taiwan Republic.
現 已 不 可 考
Since The Taiwan Republic
由 於 台 灣 民 主 國
still supported the Qing Empire,
其 實 還 是 擁 護 母 國
whose flag featured a dragon,
而 清 國 國 旗 的 圖 案 以 龍 為 主
a tiger was chosen instead.
困 此 民 主 國 國 旗 改 用 老 虎
The Taiwan Republic is claimed to be
台 灣 民 主 國 號 稱 全 亞 洲 第 一 個
the first republic in Asia.
以 民 主 為 名 的 國 家
Its reign title is Yongqing,
年 號 永 清
meaning always belonging to the Qing Empire.
意 思 是 永 遠 隸 屬 於 滿 清
President Tang Ching-Sung even declared
總 統 唐 景 崧 更 宣 言 要
The Taiwan Republic would shield the Qing Dynasty.
遙 做 清 國 的 屏 藩
Yet, how did the people of Taiwan
然 而 台 灣 人 民 對 台 灣 民 主 國
look at The Taiwan Republic?
又 有 什 麼 反 懋 咒
This was how Davidson,
當 時 在 台 北 城 的
an American reporter in Taipei
美 國 記 者 Davidson
at that time, described it.
晉 這 樣 描 述 的
I expected that the memorable day would find the streets filled
我 原 本 預 期 在 這 慶 祝 活 動 中
with holidaymakers arrayed in their best clothes.
每 個 人 都 會 峇 裝 參 與
The houses gay with flags,
家 家 戶 戶 不 但 掛 上 旗 子
and the day noisy with firecrackers.
空 氣 中 也 瀰漫 著 熬 鬧 的 鞭 炮 聲
But it was not so.
但 事 實 並 非 如 此
All things jogged along as usual.
大 家 還 是 一 如 往 常
The pretty tea girls picked their tea
筆 的 採 茶 女 漂 亮 的 採 莘
and the tea box makers and painters worked along
茶 箱 製 造 者 和 漆 匠
Not a new flag or firecracker in the settlement.
沒 有 任 何 的 旗 子 懷 掛
On this day,
這 一 天 台 灣 的 仕 紳
an official seal was cast,
共 同 出 資 鑄 成 一 顆 官 印
Tang Ching-Sung was nominated as president of The Taiwan Republic and
推 唐 景 崧 為 台 灣 民 主 國 總 統
Liu Yung-Fu as brigadier general of Tainan.
並 推 劉 永 福 為 台 南 大 將 軍
Tang knelt down twice and kowtowed six times to
唐 總 統 行 兩 路 六 叩 首 禮 受 印
receive the seal, but the Japanese Navy was approaching
但 是 當 當 天 日 本 海 當 天 日 本 海 軍 逼 近 台 灣
and the situation was tense,
情 勢 倉 平
so the unfinished ceremony
台 灣 民 主 國 還 沒 有 完 成 的 君 禮
was postponed until the following day.
延 到 隙 天 舉 行
After 21-gun salute,
君 禮 升 砲 二 十 一 響
the blue flag with a yellow tiger
隨 後 捷 上 台 灣 民 主 國
of the Taiwan Republic was hung.
藍 底 黃 虎 的 國 旗
But when the flag was raised,
但 這 只 黃 虎 旗 掛 上 去 之 後
it started to pour.
剛 好 下 了 一 場 大 雨
The tiger, painted on with yellow chalk,
旗 上 這 隻 用 黃 粉 畫 上 去 的 老 虎
was washed off.
當 場 被 淋 得 虎 型 全 都 沒 了
This seemed to foreshadow
此 情 此 景 景 似 乎 也 象 徵 著
the future of the Taiwan Republic
台 灣 民 主 國 未 來 的 命 運
On May 31, 1895, Japanese troops landed
1895 年 5 月 31 日
on Yenliao on Taiwan's Northeast Coast.
日 R 軍 由 台 灣 東 北 角 的 鹽 察 登 陸
On June 2nd,
6 月 2 日
Li Jing-Fang, the son of Li Hong-Zhang,
李 鴻 章 的 長 子 李 經 方
handed Taiwan over to Japanese representative
在 基 隆 外 海 的 船 上 辦 理 交 接
Kabayama Sukenori on a ship outside of Keelung.
把 台 灣 交 給 日 方 代 表 樺 山 資 紀
On June 3rd,
6 月 3 日
Japanese troops surrounded Keelung on land and sea.
日 軍 海 陸 包 扮 基 隆
The Regular Army of the Qing government
清 國 正 規 軍
was defeated at Shihchiuling, Keelung.
在 基 隆 獅 球 嶺 吃 了 敗 仗
The defeated soldiers rushed into Taipei,
敗 兵 一 窩 螺 擁 入 台 北 城 內
set fire and pillaged the city.
放 火 搶 劫
On the evening of June 4th,
6 月 4 日 晚 上
Tang Ching-Sung abandoned
唐 景 崧 丟 下
the 10-day old Taiwan Republic
成 立 才 十 天 的 台 灣 民 主 國
and boarded a German ship back to Xiamen.
搭 乘 一 艘 德 國 商 船 逃 回 廈 門
After Tang left,
唐 景 崧 一 起
Taipei went into chaos.
台 北 城 陷 入 一 片 混 亂
Local and foreign merchants
住 在 台 北 城 的
living in Taipei hoped the
一 些 本 島 和 外 國 商 人
Japanese army would soon arrive to restore order.
希 望 日 軍 早 一 點 進 城 維 持 秩 序
So they delegated Koo Hsien-Jung,
困 此 就 推 派
a general store owner,
在 瑞 昌 行 工 作 的 年 輕 人 韶 顯 榮
to meet with the Japanese in Keelung
去 基 隆 會 見 日 軍
and to ask them to enter the city.
請 日 軍 進 城
On June 17,
6 月 17 日
General Kabayama Sukenori of Japan
日 軍 將 領 樺 山 資 紀
at Taiwan Provincial Administration Hall in Taipei
在 台 北 城 布 政 使 司 衙 門
held a commencement ceremony
舉 行 始 政 式
and became the first Japanese Governor-General to Taiwan.
成 為 日 人 治 台 的 第 人 治 台 的 第 一 任 總 評
With that, Japan officially won
日 本 正 式 獲 得 了
its first overseas colony.
海 外 第 一 個 殖 民 地
After the ceremony,
始 政 式 之 後
Japanese troops began to move south,
日 軍 開 始 整 軍 南 下
preparing for the take-over.
準 備 完 成 接 收 全 台 的 任 務
American reporter Davidson
美 國 記 者 Davidson
described the take-over process
對 日 軍 在 台 灣 的 接 收 遇 程
as follows:
當 時 是 這 樣 描 述 的
Since Taiwan was already taken by a treaty,
日 本 人 原 以 為
that establishing themselves upon the island would be a simple matter.
便 可 以 建 立 他 們 的 地 位
They never suspected that campaign would prove
沒 想 到 會 在 台 灣 打 了 一 場
even more arduous than the north China conflict
比 先 前 在 清 國 北 方
When Japanese soldiers crossed the Tamsui River
當 日 軍 踏 過 淡 水 河
into Taoyuan, Hsinchu and Miaoli areas,
來 到 桃 竹 苗 一 帶
they were welcomed by smiling civilians
笑 臉 迎 接 他 們 的 是
waving white flags.
揮 白 旗 的 老 百 姓
However, few soldiers who fell behind
然 而 殘 餘 落 單 的 日 軍
often got attacked by militiamen.
卻 每 每 遭 受 到 民 兵 的 突 擊
Fire!
開 槍
While the Japanese troops moved south,
當 日 軍 南 下 時
some groups of heavily armed men
一 些 擁 有 武 力 的 集 團
who wanted to protect their homesteads,
基 於 保 護 家 園 的 心 理
making use of topographical advantages,
利 用 地 形 上 的 優 勤
fought a guerilla warfare with these intruders.
和 日 本 軍 隊 打 游 擊 戰
The Japanese couldn't distinguish
日 軍 一 時 分 不 出 誰 是 順 民
the civilians from the rebels.
誰 是 抗 日 份 子
So Taoyuan and East Hsinchu,
困 此 在 桃 園 ， 新 竹 東 部 地 區
were swept down without discrimination.
展 開 無 差 別 掃 蕩
But it brought the contrary effect.
如 此 一 來
It drove people
反 而 將 一 丞
who weren't anti-Japanese activists
本 來 並 不 積 極 抗 日 的 人
to join the rebels.
逼 進 了 拔 日 的 行 列
When the Japanese entered Taipei,
就 在 日 本 人 進 入 台 北 堿 的 時 候
the highly esteemed scholar Wu Te-Kung from Changhua
彰 化 德 高 望 重 的 秀 才 羔 德 功
was invited by the magistrate of Taiwan county
應 台 灣 縣 知 縣 的 邀 請
to discuss details of resistance to the Japanese.
共 商 拗 抗 事 宜
Besides recruiting local warriors and grouping them
除 了 招 募 鄉 勇 團 練 之 外
Wu also collected funds from community members
吳 德 功 也 向 地 方 人 士 籌 募 軍 餉
to keep the group going.
以 維 持 團 練 的 運 作
I heard local gents and leaders in Taoyuan, Hsinchu
我 聽 說 桃 竹 苗 地 方 仕 紳 ， 頭 人
and Miaoli like Wu Tang-Hsin, Chiang Shao-Chu,
僖 是 吳 湯 興 ， 姜 紹 祖
Huang Nan-Chiu, and Hsu Shiang
還 有 黃 南 球 ， 徐 驤 這 些 人
led warriors against the Japanese.
他 們 領 兵 與 日 軍 惡 戰
I admire their courage and strength,
勇 氣 和 情 操 實 在 令 人 很 佩 服
but what worries me now
可 是 現 在 我 最 煩 惱 的 是
is my men.
我 手 下 的 這 些 鄉 勇 們
They can hold up against
他 們 是 可 以 拗 擋
a disorderly group of bandits.
鳥 合 之 眾 的 土 匪
But regarding
但 是 若 是 具 有
Japanese troops with modern arms,
現 代 化 武 力 的 日 本 軍 隊
I don't think my people can fight against them.
我 想 還 是 不 夠
The Japanese continued to call for reinforcements
日 軍 不 斷 增 援
to drive the rebels in Taoyuan,
把 桃 竹 苗 一 常 的 拔 日 勢 力
Hsinchu and Miaoli southward.
往 南 逼 退
Finally, a large-scale fighting broke out
最 後 在 八 卦 山 一 帶
in Baguan Mountain area.
發 生 大 規 模 的 戰 鬥
The anti-Japanese militants
台 灣 民 兵 的 拔 日 勢 力
were almost wiped out
也 幾 乎 在 八 卦 山 這 一 次 戰 役 中
at this battle.
全 軍 覆 沒
Hold.
噴
They're out.
出 來 了
Fire!
開 槍
When I got back to the city,
戰 亂 後 我 回 到 城 內
90% of the houses were empty.
可 以 說 十 戶 人 家 有 九 戶 是 空 的
Trees and plants withered
草 木 枯 茗
and streets were deserted.
街 市 蕭 條
Many women lost their husbands and sons.
許 多 婦 人 失 去 了 丈 夫 ， 兒 子
An epidemic was going around.
疾 病 又 流 行
Life was even harder.
生 活 又 更 加 困 難
Being desperate,
那 時 我 實 在 慚 到 心 灰 意 冷
1 only asked for a life of peace with my family.
ˋ 《 求 與 家 人 ﹣ 岑 遇 日 Q 愿 朋 么
Being stationed in Tainan, Liu Yung-Fu, the leader
駐 守 在 台 南 的
of the Black Flags, didn't send reinforcements
黑 旗 軍 將 領 劉 永 福
to fight the Japanese in Northern and Central Taiwan
並 沒 有 派 兵 支 援 中 北 部 的 拔 日
Instead, taking advantage of the raging battle,
反 而 利 用 民 兵 和 日 軍 對 峙 時
he founded the Taiwan Republic in Tainan
成 立 了 台 南 的 台 灣 民 主 國
to reorganize defense forces and to wait for
一 方 面 整 編 防 務
the Qing government to send reinforcements.
一 方 面 等 待 清 國 的 救 援
The Black Flags are coming...
黑 軍 來 了 …
In October 1895,
1895 年 10 月
Japanese troops approached Tainan.
日 軍 兵 臨 台 南
Liu knew he could not fight them.
劉 永 福 自 知 勤 不 可 為
Following Tang Ching-Sung's footsteps
步 上 唐 景 崧 的 後 塵
he went back to China.
逃 回 清 國
At this time,
陬 J 比
the Qing government retreated completely from Taiwan.
清 國 官 方 勤 力 完 全 退 出 台 灣
Japan had many weapons.
日 本 的 武 器 很 多 件
They fought from Taipei to Tainan.
台 北 打 到 台 南 府 城
Black Flags were against White Flags.
黛 旗 白 旗 在 對 抗
The people of Taiwan were scared.
台 灣 人 看 到 很 驚 慌
To protect their lives,
為 保 護 自 己 的 性 命
they stayed at home.
躲 在 家 裡 不 敢 隨 便 出 門
One had better prepare black flags and white flags.
黑 旗 白 旗 準 備 好
It is better for a person to protect himself.
顧 自 己 的 性 命 較 安 然
What does it say?
這 是 寫 什 麼
I don't understand.
看 不 懂
Let me see.
我 看 看
What happened?
是 發 生 什 麼 事 了
The Japanese allow us
日 本 人 給 我 們 兩 年 的 時 間
to choose our nationality in two years.
選 擇 自 己 的 國 籍
Those who don't want to live under their rule
若 是 不 願 意 被 他 們 統 治 的 人
must move back to China
兩 年 之 內 都 要 移 回 去 唐 山
or to wherever the foreigners are in two years.
要 不 然 就 要 移 到 外 國 人 的 地 方
Why does it happen?
為 什 麼 有 這 種 事
How come we have to leave?
樣 為
We get used to life here but they want us to move.
在 這 裡 住 得 很 習 慧 卻 要 我 們 搬
We have a life here.
住 得 好 好 的
What should we do?
該 怎 廖 辦
Yeah.
對 啊
After taking over Taiwan,
日 本 接 收 台 灣 之 後
based on the agreements of the Treaty of Shimonoseki,
根 據 先 前 馬 關 條 約 的 協 議
Japan gave people in Taiwan a chance
准 許 台 灣 人 民
to choose their nationalities.
有 選 擇 國 籍 的 機 會
Those who did not want to become Japanese citizens
不 願 意 當 日 本 國 民 的
had to register within two years
必 須 在 兩 年 之 內 辦 理 登 記
and leave Taiwan.
選 擇 離 開 台 灣
When the deadline was up,
結 果 到 了 期 限 屆 滿 時
people who registered to leave Taiwan,
登 記 離 開 台 灣 的
were more than 4500
有 四 千 五 百 多 人
which was only 0.16% of the total population.
史 f 繁 人 史 嫚 屹 白 刈 三 零 黯 y 一 公
Even though the Japanese government issued Law 63
儕 管 隨 後 日 本 政 府 頒 布 六 三 法
and established a colonial ruling system in Taiwan
建 立 起 台 灣 總 督 總 攬 大 權 的
under the lead of Taiwan Governor-General,
殖 民 統 治 體 制
Japanese and Taiwanese living on this island
台 灣 人 和 日 本 人 在 同 一 個 島 上
had to obey different sets of laws.
分 別 適 用 不 同 的 法 律
The rights and benefits of the Taiwanese
台 灣 人 享 有 的 權 利 和 保 障
were far less than those of the Japanese.
遠 低 於 日 本 人
But most Taiwanese
但 是 大 部 分 的 台 灣 人
didn't want to abandon the homes
都 不 不 願 意 放 棄
which they have worked so hard to build.
自 己 辛 苺 開 壅 的 家 園
Taiwanese have treated Taiwan as a place
台 灣 人 已 經 把 台 灣
where they can settle down.
當 作 安 身 立 命 的 所 在
Your Excellency.
大 人
During the Qing administration,
清 國 統 治 時 期
Taiwan did not have a police force.
台 灣 沒 有 警 察
After the Japanese ruled Taiwan,
日 本 統 治 之 後
they used policemen to maintain social order
透 遇 謨 譬 察 來 維 持 治 釵 泌 安
and to carry out administrative orders.
並 且 貫 徹 行 政 命 令
The Japanese government gave these policemen great power.
日 本 政 府 賦 予 警 察 極 大 權 力
What one did every day
日 常 生 3 活 中 的 一 舉 一 動
could be interfered by the policemen.
譫 察 都 可 以 千 浬
Let me weigh that.
我 秤 秤 看
Japanese police were very strict.
日 本 警 察 執 勤 的 態 度 非 常 嚴 苛
Sometimes they exercised violence.
有 時 甚 至 任 意 鞭 打 人 民
A catty and a half.
這 一 斤 半
Your Excellency.
大 人
How much does that weigh?
這 個 多 重
One catty.
一 斤
Is that so?
是 這 樣 嗎
You bastard.
混 蛋
What's your name?
史 什 麼 名 字
Chen Ching-Chung.
陳 慶 中
At that time Japanese policemen
當 時 的 日 本 員 議
used local hooligans
春 ! 用 台 灣 當 地
as agents
一 批 地 痞 流 泰 做 幫 凶
to abuse and harm Taiwanese.
以 從 事 殘 害 自 己 同 胞 的 工 作
So those working for the Japanese were called
所 以 台 灣 同 胞 罵 他 們 為 三 腳 仔
"Three Legs" or Japanese lackeys.
也 號 是 日 本 走 狗 的 意 思
Seven to eight years
日 本 接 收 台 灣 之 後 的
after the Japanese rule,
七 到 八 年 之 間
local powers and leaders,
台 灣 社 會 上 的 地 方 勢 力 和 角 頭
in order to protect their profits,
為 了 保 護 既 得 的 利 益
began a long-term fight against the Japanese
和 日 本 人 展 開 了 長 期 對 抗
and hid.
躲 起 來 了
The Japanese government issued
日 本 政 府 一 方 面 頒 布
the Gangster Penalty Order to execute bandits.
處 以 死 刑 的 匪 徒 刑 罰 令
It also offered favorable conditions
一 方 面 又 提 供 優 厚 的 條 件
to people who surrender.
加 以 招 降
Then it waited for the right time to counterattack.
等 待 時 機 成 熟 就 發 動 圍 剿
Chien Ta-Shih, Ko Tie-Hu and Lin Shao-Mao,
簡 大 獅 ， 柯 鐵 虎 ， 林 少 貓 等
who later came to be known
被 後 人 稱 為
as the three great anti-Japanese heroes,
找 日 三 猩 的 反 拔 首 腦
were exterminated one by one.
就 這 樣 一 一 被 癮 滅
As for the gents and scholars,
對 於 仕 紳 文 人 階 級
the Japanese government tried to win their support
日 本 政 府 採 取 積 極 攏 絡 的 策 略
so as to form a new group of local leaders.
以 建 立 地 方 上 新 的 領 導 階 層
In 1896,
1896 年
military policeman Takahashi and CaptainTogo
憲 兵 高 橋 與 藤 吾 大 尉
came to my house.
來 我 家 裡 拜 芥
I told them I was old
我 是 以 我 年 紀 太 大
and sick to turn down the offer.
雨 且 又 生 病 為 理 由 推 辭
In the spring of 1897, I didn't expect
沒 想 到 說 1897 年 的 春 天
Murakami Yoshio, the prefect of Taichung county,
台 中 縣 的 知 事 村 上 義 雁
would more than one time send his interpreter
好 幾 次 都 派 遣 他 的 通 譯
to see me.
來 到 我 家 裡
This time I didn't dare decline.
這 次 我 是 不 敢 再 推 辭 了
So that's how I became a counselor.
所 以 我 就 去 做 參 事 了
In order to profit more
為 了 從 台 灣 這 塊 殖 民 地
from the colony of Taiwan,
獲 得 更 大 的 經 濟 利 益
during the Japanese rule,
日 本 統 治 期 間
the Japanese completed several infrastructures
在 台 灣 完 成 多 項 基 礎 建 設
At the end of 1895, when Goto Shimpei was
1895 年 底
health consultant at the Office of Governor-General,
後 藤 新 平 擔 任 總 督 衛 生 顧 問 時
he hired Mr. Burton, a British engineer,
延 聘 英 國 籍 技 師 巴 爾 頓
to help construct tap water and drainage systems.
來 台 煙 建 自 來 水 和 下 水 道 工 程
Here and here
這 裡 和 這 裡
This will supply fresh water
這 個 會 提 供
for the people of the city.
這 個 場 市 的 人 民 乾 淨 的 水
How long will it take?
雷 要 花 多 久 的 時 間
It will take several years.
需 要 幾 年 吧
It depends on whether everything goes smoothly.
就 看 這 一 切 的 進 度 順 不 順 利
Good...
好 …
In 1898,
1898 年
the waterworks of Taipei were completed.
台 北 自 來 水 道 工 程 完 工
Tap water officially entered Taiwan's history.
水 道 水 正 式 流 入 台 灣 的 歷 史
With that,
隨 著 水 道 水 流 入 台 灣
Taiwan
台 灣 社 會 經 歷 了 一 場
metamorphosed into a modern society.
巨 大 的 現 代 化 的 蛻 變
In 1900,
明 治 33 年
Count Kodama Gentaro, Taiwan Governor-General,
台 灣 總 督 府 男 爵
held a conference on cultural issues.
兒 玉 源 太 郎 閣 下 舉 行 揚 文 會
More than 150 provincial graduates
全 台 灣 有 一 百 五 十 多 位
and tributary scholars were invited to this event.
舉 人 ， 貢 生 受 到 邀 請
I took a northbound train from Hsinchu.
我 從 新 竹 搭 乘 火 車 北 上
It left at 9 o'clock
九 點 發 車
and arrived at Tataocheng at 12.
十 二 點 就 搔 達 大 稷 埕
It was like magic
真 像 是 變 法 術 一 般
for the distance of two places to be shortened.
將 兩 地 的 距 離 拉 近
I guess with water and fire
人 家 所 謂 水 氣 通 火 氣
the train runs faster than the light.
焗 電 追 迅 風
That should be what people mean.
應 該 就 是 這 個 意 思
In 1900, the Office of Taiwan Governor-General
1900 年
held a conference on cultural issues
總 督 府 舉 辦 揚 文 會 之 旅
Wu Te-Kung and other scholars took a train
吳 德 功 一 行 人 便 搭 乘 火 車
to visit the new armaments and facilities
參 觀 了 日 本 當 局
the Japanese government constructed in Taiwan.
在 台 灣 建 立 的 新 軍 備 ， 新 設 3
This is great.
真 是 太 好 了
For the city of Taipei,
對 台 北 國 來 說
This is very convenient
這 是 很 方 便 的
Of course,
乏 茜 爭 ﹣ ‧ 蒿 秦 夾
For the Japanese Empire,
對 大 日 本 常 國 而 言
this is an outstanding achievement.
是 很 了 不 起 的
I'm very happy.
真 是 太 高 興 了
We visited a battleship at the Keelung Harbor
我 們 到 基 隆 港 參 觀 戰 艦
and saw the army performing drills.
又 去 看 陸 軍 操 練
The machines at the sawmill
鋸 木 所 的 機 械
were as fast as lightening.
敏 捷 的 像 旋 風
The camphor plant was also very advanced.
遼 有 樟 腦 製 造 所 設 備 真 先 進
Camphor products are machine packed like cigarettes,
隨 包 隨 裝 ， 像 做 洋 莎 一 樣
which saves a lot of time and energy.
實 在 是 省 時 又 省 力
It was amazing.
真 的 讓 人 想 不 到
We also visited the electricity plant
還 有 我 們 去 參 觀 電 火 所
and the pharmaceutical plant,
製 藥 所
demonstrating the wonders of chemistry and physics.
實 在 令 人 感 到 化 學 物 理 的 奧 妙
The hospital trained doctors and nurses,
還 有 醫 院 訓 練 公 醫 生 ， 看 護 婦
which set precedents.
實 在 是 開 本 島 風 氣 之 先 例
My daughter is getting married.
我 要 嫁 女 時 了
I see.
這 樣 啊
Congratulations...
羲 喜 …
Let me give you a discount.
我 再 幫 你 算 便 宜 一 丞
Thank you...
多 謝 …
In 1899,
1899 年
The Bank of Taiwan was founded.
日 本 成 立 台 灣 銀 行
Monetary law and currency reform were carried out.
施 行 貨 幣 法 ， 改 革 幣 制
In the past, the Taiwanese thought only coins made of
過 去 台 灣 人 民 認 定 遇 去 台 灣 人 民 認 定 龍 銀 ， 銅 幣
precious metals such as silver and bronze
這 種 有 價 金 屬 所 做 成 的 貨 幣
were of value.
才 是 有 價 值 的
After the monetary system was unified,
幣 制 統 一 之 後
they began to understand
台 灣 人 民 也 逐 漸 接 取
the modern financial concept
紙 幣 是 有 價 貨 幣 的
that paper money was also value-based currency.
現 代 金 融 觀 念
During the Japanese administration,
日 治 初 期
to develop agriculture in Taiwan and industry in Japan
以 農 業 台 灣 ， 工 業 日 本
was its economic policy.
藍 政 菜 ﹣ 去 ※ K c﹤ 下 為
In Taiwan new sugar plants were constructed
在 台 灣 興 建 新 式 糖 廠
to replace old sugar mills.
取 代 舊 式 的 糖 廊
The tall chimneys of new sugar plants
新 式 糟 廠 的 煙 囝
became Taiwan's new landmarks.
變 成 台 灣 的 新 地 標
Taiwan's sugar industry flourished.
台 灣 的 糖 業 蓬 勃 發 展
During World War I,
到 了 一 次 世 界 大 戰 期 間
the production of beet sugar stopped in Europe.
歐 洲 的 甜 菜 糖 停 產
As a result, Taiwan's sugar sold not only in Asia,
使 得 台 灣 糖 不 僅 行 銷 亞 洲
but also in Europe, America and Australia.
甚 至 擴 大 到 歐 ， 美 和 澳 洲
It was the golden time of Taiwan's sugar industry.
可 說 是 台 灣 糖 業 的 黃 金 時 期
Opium was gradually prohibited.
對 鴉 片 採 取 漸 禁 政 策
It was not abolished until the 1930s.
至 1930 年 代 之 後 才 革 除
Foot-binding and queues,
纏 足 ， 辮 鬢
however, were meant to be abolished at once.
則 掌 取 立 即 革 除 政 篆
It, nevertheless, took several years
但 台 灣 人 民 在 數 年 之 內
for the practices to end.
才 逐 漸 革 除
The abolishment of foot-binding
鑣 足 的 解 放
not only liberated the women of Taiwan,
不 但 解 放 了 台 灣 婦 女
but also supply
同 時 也 提 供 了
female workforce for the Taiwanese society.
台 灣 社 會 的 婦 女 勞 動 力
This was the beginning of a profound effect
這 是 影 響 深 遠 的
on the emancipation of Taiwanese women.
台 灣 婦 女 解 放 的 開 始
In southern mountains of China,
今 我 中 國 南 陵
was born a holy ruler and talented subject
天 生 名 聖 之 君 ， 莫 賢 之 臣
who has the ability to rule a country,
文 有 經 天 濟 世 之 才
and the ambition to bring peace to the country.
武 有 安 邦 定 國 之 志
He has his right-hand man and faithful subjects,
股 肱 棟 樑 ， 賢 臣 輔 佐
and the help of three religions
三 教 助 法
(Buddhism, Confucianism, and Taoism).
聖 神 仙 佛
Holy gods and Buddha come to the world to preach.
下 凡 傳 道
He has myriads of disciples
門 徒 萬 千
and can do many things.
變 化 無 窮
The heavenly master comes.
天 師 降 臨
All the people should follow him.
不 分 玉 石
But as Taiwan underwent modernization,
但 是 在 台 灣 進 入 現 代 化 的 過 程 中
an anti-Japanese rebellion with religious coloring
民 間 卻 發 生 了 一 件
erupted in 1915:
帶 著 濃 厚 宗 教 色 彩 的 拔 日 事 件
the Xilai An Incident.
那 就 是 1915 年 的 西 來 庵 事 件
Under the imperial decree of the Taming Compassion State,
大 明 慈 憎 國 奉 旨
I, Commander Yu, will bring peace to Taiwan.
平 台 征 伐 天 下 大 元 帥 余 示 諭
In the 5th lunar month of 1915
今 年 乙 卯 五 月
The Japanese have been in Taiwan for 20 years,
倭 賊 到 台 二 十 年 已 滿
but their days are numbered.
氣 數 將 盡
Neither the heaven nor the earth will tolerate them.
天 地 不 容
Gods and men are in anger.
神 人 共 愷
Damn!...
可 惡 …
I will rise up and fight on mandate of the heaven.
本 帥 奉 天 舉 義 討 伐
Yu Ching-Fang used folk religion
余 清 芳 以 民 間 俸 仰 的 方 式
to appeal to the people.
號 召 群 真
He declared that divine power had appeared in Taiwan
宣 稱 台 灣 已 出 現 神 主
and would establish Taming Compassion State.
將 建 立 大 明 慈 悲 國
His followers increased day by day,
由 於 信 眾 日 增
which alarmed the Japanese intelligence.
驚 動 日 本 情 治 當 局
The Japanese government commanded to arrest
於 是 下 令 通 緝 余 清 芳 等 人
Yu and his followers
余 清 芳 率 眸
who retreated to Xilai An (Xilai Temple),
送 入 今 台 南 玉 井 ， 楔 西 一 帶
nowadays' Yujing and Nanshi areas in Tainan.
在 西 來 庵 倉 促 發 動 攻 擊
With traditional swords and religious instruments,
以 傳 統 的 刀 劍 和 宗 教 法 器
they fought modernized Japanese troops.
對 抗 日 本 現 代 化 的 軍 隊
We regretted deeply.
吾 著 抱 惑
Furiously killing people,
猖狂 造 罪
the Japanese
日 本 倭 賊
lost their humanities.
全 無 人 性
Being protected by gods,
神 體 護 身
I enforced justice on behalf of the Heaven.
替 天 行 道
What did he say?
時 說 什 麼
Fire!
開 槍
The Xilai An Incident
西 來 庵 事 件
was the resistance of the pre-modern people
是 前 現 代 社 會 人 民
against a modernized police force.
對 現 代 化 軍 警 的 拯 抗
Then Japan had finished the Meiji Restoration.
當 時 日 本 的 明 治 維 新 已 經 完 成
The 1911 Revolution in China
中 國 的 辛 亥 革 命
had also come to an end.
也 已 經 告 一 段 落
Yet Yu and his party
嫚 928 坦
still imagined a Boxer-type rebellion.
卻 還 幻 想 著 義 和 團 式 的 反 抗
Even though they fought heroically,
雖 然 慣 慨 抗 日
their rebellion still ended in tragedy.
卻 是 悲 劇 一 場
The end of the Xilai An Incident
西 來 庵 事 件 結 束
marked the end of
為 台 灣 漢 人 的 武 裝 抗 日
armed anti-Japanese forces in Taiwan.
畫 下 句 點
The new generation of Taiwanese
此 後 接 受 日 本 西 式 教 育 的
who received Japan's western-styled education
新 一 代 台 灣 人
launched political and social movements
所 展 間 的 政 治 社 會 運 動
that were quite different in spirit and in contents.
其 精 神 與 內 涵 都 大 不 相 同
At the beginning of the Japanese rule,
日 本 政 府 治 台 初 期
the government resorted to pacifying the aborigines
對 台 灣 原 住 民 採 取 安 撫 的 策 略
and make investigations into their forest resources,
並 且 對 原 住 民 居 住 的 地 區
cultures, and customs
展 開 林 地 資 源
of the areas they lived in.
以 及 風 俗 文 化 的 調 查
Only when Sakuma Samata became the 5th Taiwan
直 到 第 五 任 總 督 佐 久 間 巨 馬 太
Governor-General, did the aborigine suppression begin.
才 展 開 鎮 壓 原 住 民 的 行 動
With superior military backup,
日 本 人 以 優 勢 武 力 為 後 盾
the Japanese moved the Qing Empire's Detaining Line
將 清 國 設 置 的 隘 勇 線
to the aboriginal territory.
向 原 住 民 的 活 動 領 域 推 進
Some major sections
重 要 路 段
even had electric barb wires
甚 至 將 鐵 絲 網 通 電
to prevent aborigines from crossing.
阻 止 原 住 民 越 過 隘 勇 線
In 1910
到 了 1910 年
when the Japanese government
日 本 政 府
finished deploying the Detaining Line,
完 成 隘 勇 線 的 布 署 之 後
they began armed attacks on aborigine tribes.
就 對 原 住 民 鄧 落 發 動 武 裝 攻 擊
The aborigines could not fight the armed Japanese.
原 住 民 在 日 本 優 勢 武 力 下
Anti-Japanese activities were gradually quelled.
抗 日 活 動 逐 漸 被 弭 平
In 1915,
到 了 1915 年 間
aborigine tribes in Taiwan,
台 灣 的 原 住 民 部 落
like the Han Chinese,
和 漢 人 社 會 一 樣
were under the control of the Japanese government.
被 掩 控 在 一 個 國 家 體 制 之 內
Good morning.
旱 安
Good afternoon.
午 安
Good evening.
晚 安
A handsome man.
瀟 灑
Issho naru means to sleep together.
伊 休 那 魯 是 一 起 睡
Iro otoko means a handsome man.
以 羅 多 印 是 緣 投 桑
Kirei onna. Come on.
基 雷 歐 嘈 那 ， 來
Kirei onna means a beautiful woman.
基 雷 歐 嘿 那 是 美 查 棻
The teacher is coming...
老 師 來 了
Dad, the teacher is here.
阿 爹 ， 老 師 來 了
In 1898,
1898 年
the Japanese government turned
日 本 政 府 把 教 授 日 語 的
Japanese centers into six-year public schools
國 語 傳 習 所
offering a new form of education.
改 為 六 年 制 新 式 教 育 的 公 學 校
But to Taiwanese families at that time,
但 是 日 治 初 期 的 台 灣 家 庭
since this new form of education
認 為 新 式 教 育
no longer offered an imperial examination system,
不 再 有 科 舉 考 試 的 出 路
they'd rather have their children tend farming.
寧 可 讓 小 孩 留 在 家 裡 幫 忙 務 農
So Japanese elementary school teachers
於 是 日 本 的 小 學 老 師
had to pay house calls
還 得 要 登 門 拜 詮
to persuade parents
勸 家 長 讓 小 孩 接 受
to send their children to school.
日 本 的 新 式 教 育
Good afternoon, everyone.
大 家 午 安
Good afternoon, Teacher.
老 師 ， 午 安
After 1910,
1910 年 之 後
when the Japanese rule became stable,
因 為 日 本 的 統 治 慢 慢 穩 固
Taiwanese families were more willing
台 灣 家 庭 才 比 較 願 意
to send their children to these new schools.
讓 小 孩 進 入 新 式 教 育 的 公 學 校
After six-year study at the elementary school,
甚 至 在 六 年 畢 業 後
some even attended vocational or teacher's schools.
繼 續 就 讀 職 業 學 校 或 師 範 學 校
The new education system
新 式 教 育 的 內 容
unavoidably tried to instill ideas
雖 然 免 不 了 要 灌 輸
of Japan's greatness
日 本 國 家 的 偉 大
to attain the goal of assimilating Taiwanese.
貫 徹 同 化 的 目 標
It also provided common knowledge,
但 也 有 更 多 的 生 活 知 識
and liberal arts courses,
與 人 文 藝 術 課 程
which developed the Taiwanese's
提 弅 了 台 灣 人 的
scientific spirit and world views.
科 學 精 神 與 世 界 觀
It also built a strong foundation
也 為 後 來 的 文 化 社 會 改 革 運 動
for the future cultural and social reform movements.
打 下 了 重 要 的 基 礎
The Japanese Empire treated Taiwan,
日 本 帝 國 對 待 他 們 海 外 的
their first colony overseas,
第 一 個 殖 民 地 台 灣
with benevolence and strictness.
所 用 的 恩 威 並 施 的 治 理 方 式
Compared with the passivity of the Qing Empire,
和 消 極 統 治 台 灣 的 清 帝 國 相 比
this treatment was far more aggressive.
就 顧 得 積 極 多 了
It was a totalitarian rule
這 是 一 種 由 上 到 下
that opted to control the society
天 羅 地 網 般
from top to bottom.
進 行 社 會 控 制 的 中 央 極 權
The various forces
原 本 存 在 於
that had existed in local communities
台 灣 民 間 的 各 種 勢 力
were consequently demolished.
也 困 此 被 徽 底 消 滅
Taiwan was a pre-modern society
台 灣 由 原 本 鬆 敬
that was lax and closed off.
不 相 往 來 的 前 現 代 社 會
But under the Japanese rule,
在 日 本 殖 民 統 治 下
It gradually became
漸 漸 成 為 一 個 被 轟 聚 在 一 起
a coherent and modern society.
有 整 體 國 家 惹 覺 的 現 代 社 會
In 1919,
1919 年
the Japanese government carried out
日 本 政 府 宣 布 內 地 延 長 主 義
“ Japanese extensionism, ” an assimilation policy,
也 號 是 要 把 台 灣
which would turn Taiwan into a part of Japan,
看 作 是 日 本 的 一 部 分
and would treat it as equally as Japan proper.
要 和 日 本 本 地 一 視 同 仁
That year, the Office of Governor-General,
同 年 象 徵 日 本 在 台
the highest Japanese government institution
最 高 統 治 機 構 的 總 督 府
in Taiwan, was completed.
興 建 完 工
The Japanese rule of Taiwan
日 本 對 台 的 統 治
reached a stable stage.
也 進 入 了 一 個 安 定 的 局 面